Finding Aid for Program of Nurse Anesthesia (University of Michigan) records, 1919-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Program of Nurse Anesthesia (University of Michigan) records 1919-1987
University of Michigan. Program of Nurse Anesthesia.
1.0 linear ft. (in 2 boxes)
University of Michigan program established in 1919 for the graduate training of nurses in anesthesia, closed in 1987. Records include Correspondence, newspaper clippings, and other papers containing some general information about the history and administration of the program (especially during the 1970s and 1980s), and the eventual closure of the program in 1987.
994 Bimu 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were donated by Robert B. Powell (Donor No. 8750 ) in 1998.
The collection is open for research except for the student records series. The files in the student record series are restricted for 75 years from the date of creation.
The Nurse Anesthesiology Program of the University of Michigan was established in 1919 for the graduate training of nurses in anesthesia at the University Hospital. Graduates of the program received a Certificate in Nurse Anesthesia. The program had several name changes during the course of its existence; however, the exact dates as to when these changes took place are uncertain. The original name of the program was the Special Course in Anesthesia. From the correspondence in the record group, the name appears to have changed sometime during the period from 1951 to 1952 to the School for Nurse Anesthetists. This name was used interchangeably with the names the School of Nurse Anesthesia and the School of Anesthesia from 1964 to 1979. The final name of the program, the Program of Nurse Anesthesia, was being used by 1980.
Laura Davis was the first Director of the School, and also served as an instructor in the twelve month program. Lillian Baird succeeded Laura Davis as Director of the School in 1938, and during her time as director the program was lengthened to eighteen months in order to comply with the American Association of Nurse Anesthetists' accreditation standards. Eleanor Cunningham served as the Director of the School from 1964 to 1974. The program was eventually lengthened to twenty-four months in 1975, a change which was proposed by David Ely (Director from 1974 to 1976). An optional master's degree program, which was offered through the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies, was established in 1977 by Neil Morse (Director from 1976-1978) and enabled interested students to obtain a Master of Science degree in Education. After Neil Morse left, there were two Acting Directors for the school while the search for a new Director was made. Robert B. Powell became the Director in 1979, and remained in that position until the program's controversial closing for financial and political reasons in 1987. The training of nurse anesthesiologists at the University of Michigan ceased with the termination of the program.
The records of the Program of Nurse Anesthesia include Correspondence, newspaper clippings, and other papers containing some general information about the history and administration of the program (especially during the 1970s and 1980s), and the eventual closure of the program in 1987. The records are divided into two series: Administrative Files and Student Records.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Program of Nurse Anesthesia.; Anesthesiology--Study and Teaching--Michigan.; Nursing--Study and teaching.
- Administrative Files
  The Administrative Files series contains some general information about the program, information regarding the American Association of Nurse Anesthetists' (AANA) accreditation of the program during its later years (1973-1985), an administrative manual from the 1980's, and correspondence. The three bound reports that are included in this series (the Self Evaluation Study, Enclosures to Self Evaluation Study, and Response to Summary Report) were prepared in 1985 as part of the AANA's accreditation process. This series also contains files regarding three important events in the program's later history: the expansion of the program from eighteen months to twenty four months (1975), the proposal for the addition of a Master of Science in Anesthesia (1982-1984), and information regarding the eventual closure of the program in 1987.
  - Information About the Program, 1919-1982 (Box 1)
  - AANA Accreditation, 1973-1985 (Box 1)
  - Administrative Manual-Volume I (Box 1)
  - Administrative Manual-Volume II (Box 1)
  - Closure of Program, 1985-1987 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1919-1976 (Box 1)
  - Expansion of Program from 18 Months to 24 Months, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Master's Degree Addition, 1982-1984 (Box 1)
  - Response to Summary Report, July, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Self Evaluation Study (with enclosures), January, 1985 (Box 1)
- Student Records
  [Restricted access; student records closed for 75 years from date of creation]
  The Student Records series contains lists (both alphabetical and chronological by month and year graduated) of the graduates of the program from 1919 to 1987, as well as copies of the individual student's applications. The applications are grouped by the dates they were signed by the students, and photographs of the students are attached to the corresponding applications.
  - Lists of Graduates of the Program, 1919-1987 (Box 2)
  - Student Applications
    - 1923-1928 (Box 2)
      [Restricted until January 2003 ]
    - 1930-1939 (Box 2)
      [Restricted until January 2014 ]
    - 1940-1949 (Box 2)
      [Restricted until January 2024 ]
    - 1950-1959 (Box 2)
      [Restricted until January 2034 ]
    - 1960-1969 (Box 2)
      [Restricted until January 2044 ]
    - 1970-1979 (Box 2)
      [Restricted until January 2054 ]
    - 1980-1985 (Box 2)
      [Restricted until January 2060 ]